<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MAGs on Alexander Lab @ WHOI</title>
    <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/tags/mags/</link>
    <description>Recent content in MAGs on Alexander Lab @ WHOI</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/tags/mags/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Eukaryotic Metagenome Assembled Genomes (MAGs)</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/projects/euk-mags/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/projects/euk-mags/</guid>
      <description>Protists, or eukaryotic microbes, are key players in marine ecosystems, encompassing primary producers (phytoplankton), mixotrophs, and heterotrophs. Similar to their prokaryotic microbial counterparts (bacteria and archaea), many protists cannot be cultured, making the direct study of their biology in the lab challenging. Molecular and genomic approaches, particularly those applied to whole, mixed communities (e.g. metagenomics), have shed light on the ecological roles, evolutionary histories, and physiological capabilities of these organisms. Metagenomic analyses have traditionally focused on the analysis of species and gene content and shifts in relative abundance between samples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcriptional Basis of Sinking</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/projects/cosci/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/projects/cosci/</guid>
      <description>During the DeepDOM cruise, we transited through the Amazon plume. The Amazon river is responsible for ~15% of all fresh water input to the world&amp;rsquo;s oceans. Consequently, this region represents a unique biogeochemical environment, characterized by low salinity and rich in terrestrial carbon and nutrients. In the low salinity lens of the plume, we discovered a blooming species of Coscinodiscus, a centric diatom. We were able to monitor its physiological status in situ, perform field incubation experiments, and recover and isolate from this bloom to study in culture.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>