<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Alexander Lab @ WHOI</title>
    <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Alexander Lab @ WHOI</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 15:25:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using `rclone` to manage data on a remote server via Google Drive</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2020-05-30-rclone/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 15:25:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2020-05-30-rclone/</guid>
      <description>There are a lot of reasons to set up Google Drive integration on your remote HPC system. In particular if your institution has provided you access to G Suite, there is a lot of storage available on Google Drive. Sometimes you might want to access files from multiple HPC systems, or have them at your fingertips on your local machine in addition to a remote server. This blog post will go over how to set up and use rclone with Google Drive on your remote server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alexander Lab at OSM 2020</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2020-osm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 13:00:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2020-osm/</guid>
      <description>I am heading to Ocean Sciences Meeting next week in San Diego along with Laura Blum, an undergraduate researcher doing her thesis research with Maria Pachiadaki, Erin Eggleston, and myself. We have two presentations (that are bookending the meeting &amp;ndash; Monday and Friday) that are both related to work we have been doing looking at MAGs from the larger size fraction metagenomic datasets generated as part of the Tara Expedition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bioinformatics in Light of Intercallibration</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2020-calibrating-omics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 14:38:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2020-calibrating-omics/</guid>
      <description>A month ago, I had the opportunity to participate in the Oceans Carbon Biogeochemistry Nucleic Acids ‘Omics Standardization and Intercalibration Workshop hosted at UNC Chappel Hill. The goal of this workshop was to come together as a community and discuss the challenges (and opportunities) we face as we continue to gather samples across the ocean for various nucleic acid omics (metabarcoding or amplicon sequencing, metagenomics, and metatranscriptomics). As was done through GeoTraces, intercomparability of measures requires consistency of measures ntercallibration is absolutely necesseary</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running Jupyter Notebooks Remotely Using Windows</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2019-07-24-slurm-win/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2019 15:25:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2019-07-24-slurm-win/</guid>
      <description>Harriet wrote an awesome blog post here about how to use a Jupyter notebook connected to a remote server via SSH tunneling. Unfortunately, depending on your existing setup on your computer, you may have a few extra steps to wrangle if you have a PC. In this blog post, I&amp;rsquo;ll highlight what you should do after you get the Jupyter notebook running on the remote. In other words, you should have already gotten to the step where you spin up the Jupyter notebook, as in:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping my R life organized</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/anaconda-r-sarah/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2019 16:06:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/anaconda-r-sarah/</guid>
      <description>I recently found myself setting up a new computer, spinning up ~23864283.34 new projects in R, and wanting to stay somewhat organized in the process. After doing some digging, I decided to give Anaconda environments a try to have the ability to run different versions of R and do this across R on the command line, RStudio, and jupyter notebooks (IRKernel). I have decided to share my process.
Installing Anaconda First, let&amp;rsquo;s make sure Anaconda is installed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running Jupyter Notebooks Remotely with Slurm</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2019-03-08_jpn_slurm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 18:30:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2019-03-08_jpn_slurm/</guid>
      <description>I run the bulk of my bioinformatic analyses remotely on a server or HPC, as they require more computational power or space than I have on my local computer. Rather than transfer the intermediate byproducts of these analyses (which may often be very large) to my local machine, I prefer to examine and analyze the data remotely using Jupyter. As jupyter notebook are browser-based, if you run the command jupyter notebook on a remote machine you will not be able to automatically interact with the jupyter dashboard as you do not have access to a browser on the remote machine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, world.</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 18:35:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/first/</guid>
      <description>Two months ago, I started in the Biology Department at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution as an Assistant Scientist. The processes has been otherworldly. Suddenly I find myself the steward of my own ship (read: lab). My emotional state seems to oscillate between excited exhilaration and existential terror (O 3 kHz). I have spent the last 11 (or more) years working towards this very moment&amp;ndash; so it is surreal to have officially arrived.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>