<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bioinformatics on Alexander Lab @ WHOI</title>
    <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/tags/bioinformatics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bioinformatics on Alexander Lab @ WHOI</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 15:25:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/tags/bioinformatics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using anvi&#39;o in interactive mode</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2022-10-24_anvio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 15:25:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/post/2022-10-24_anvio/</guid>
      <description>Anvi&amp;rsquo;o is a powerful tool for analyzing and vizualizing &amp;lsquo;omics data, much of which relies on one&amp;rsquo;s ability to visualize those data. On Poseidon, it can sometimes be difficult to work with these kinds of plotting tools, because we&amp;rsquo;re working on the command line. To use anvi&amp;rsquo;o interactively on Poseidon, we need to go through a few extra steps.
I&amp;rsquo;ll walk you through the whole installation of anvi&amp;rsquo;o here from start to finish!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QIIME 2: Reproducible, interactive, scalable, and extensible microbiome data science</title>
      <link>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/publication/bolyen2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderlabwhoi.github.io/publication/bolyen2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract We present QIIME 2, an open-source microbiome data science platform accessible to users spanning the microbiome research ecosystem, from scientists and engineers to clinicians and policy makers. QIIME 2 provides new features that will drive the next generation of microbiome research. These include interactive spatial and temporal analysis and visualization tools, support for metabolomics and shotgun metagenomics analysis, and automated data provenance tracking to ensure reproducible, transparent microbiome data science.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>